<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc"
  xmlns:e="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Spec/ElementSyntax" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="c.archive-manifest">

  <title>p:archive-manifest</title>

  <para>The <code>p:archive-manifest</code> creates an XML manifest file describing the contents of
    the archive appearing on its <port>source</port> port.</para>

  <p:declare-step type="p:archive-manifest">
    <p:input port="source" primary="true" content-types="any" sequence="false"/>
    <p:output port="result" primary="true" content-types="application/xml" sequence="false"/>
    <p:option name="format" as="xs:QName?"/>
    <p:option name="parameters" as="map(xs:QName, item()*)?"/>
    <p:option name="relative-to" as="xs:anyURI?"/>
  </p:declare-step>

  <para>The <code>p:archive-manifest</code> step inspects the archive appearing on its
      <port>source</port> port and outputs a manifest describing the contents of the archive on its
      <port>result</port> port. </para>

  <para>The format of the archive is determined as follows:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>If the <option>format</option> option is specified, this determines the format of the
        archive. Implementations <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> support the <biblioref linkend="zip"/>
        format, specified with the value <code>zip</code>. <impl>It is
            <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm> what other formats are supported.</impl>
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>If no <option>format</option> option is specified or if its value is the empty sequence,
        the archive's format will be determined by the step, using the <code>content-type</code>
        document-property of the document on the <port>source</port> port and/or by inspecting its
        contents. <impl>It is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm> how the step determines
          the archive's format.</impl> Implementations <rfc2119>should</rfc2119> recognize archives
        in <biblioref linkend="zip"/> format. </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para><error code="C0085">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the format of the archive 
    does not match the specified format, cannot be understood, determined and/or processed.</error></para>

  <para>The <option>parameters</option> option can be used to supply parameters to control the
    archive manifest generation. <impl>The semantics of the keys and the allowed values for these
      keys are <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl>
    <error code="C0079">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the map
        <option>parameters</option> contains an entry whose key is defined by the implementation and
      whose value is not valid for that key.</error></para>

  <para>The <option>relative-to</option> option, when present, is used in creating the value of the
    manifest's <code>c:entry/@href</code> attribute. If the option is relative, it is made absolute 
    against the base URI of the element on which it is specified (<tag>p:with-option</tag> or the step 
    in case of a syntactic shortcut value). <error code="D0064">It is a <glossterm>dynamic 
      error</glossterm> if the base URI is not both absolute and valid according to <biblioref
        linkend="rfc3986"/>.</error></para>

  <para>The generated manifest has the format as described in <xref linkend="cv.archive-manifest"/>.
    Implementations <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> supply an <tag>c:entry</tag> element and its
      <code>name</code> and <code>content-type</code> attributes for every entry in the archive. The
    value of the generated manifest's <code>c:entry/@href</code> attribute will be determined in the
    same way as a base URI of an unarchived document by <xref linkend="c.unarchive"/>. <error
      code="C0120">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the <option>relative-to</option>
      option is not present and the document on the <port>source</port> port does not have a base
      URI.</error>
    <impl>Additional information provided for entries in <tag>p:archive-manifest</tag> is
        <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl></para>

  <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

  <simplesect>
    <title>Document properties</title>
    <para feature="archive-manifest-preserves-none">No document properties are preserved.
The manifest has no <property>base-uri</property>.</para>
  </simplesect>
</section>
