<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:e="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Spec/ElementSyntax"
         xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:id="c.json-join"
         version="5.0-extension w3c-xproc">
<title>p:json-join</title>

<para>The <code>p:json-join</code> step joins the sequence of documents on port <port>source</port>
into a single JSON document (an array) appearing on port <port>result</port>. If the sequence on
port <code>source</code> is empty, the empty sequence is returned on
port <code>result</code>.</para>

<p:declare-step type="p:json-join">
  <p:input port="source" sequence="true" content-types="any"> </p:input>
  <p:output port="result" content-types="application/json"/>
  <p:option name="flatten-to-depth" as="xs:string?" select="'0'"/>
</p:declare-step>

<para>The step inspects the documents on port <port>source</port> in turn to create the
  resulting array:</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>If the document under inspection is a JSON document representing an array, the array is copied 
     to the resulting array according to the setting of option <option>flatten-to-depth</option>.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>For every other type of JSON document, for XML documents, HTML documents, or text
    documents, their XDM representation is appended to the resulting array.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para><impl>It is <glossterm>implementation defined</glossterm> if <code>p:json-join</code> is
      able to process document types not mentioned yet, i.e. types of binary documents.</impl> If a processor
      supports a given type of documents, an entry is created as described above. <error code="C0111">
        It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if a document of an unsupported document type appears on 
        port <port>source</port> of <code>p:json-join</code>.</error>
    </para>  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
  
<para>The option <option>flatten-to-depth</option> controls whether and to which
depth members of an array appearing on port <port>source</port> are flattened.
<error code="C0119">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if <option>flatten</option> is
neither “<literal>unbounded</literal>”, nor a string that may be cast to a non-negative integer.</error>
An integer value of <literal>0</literal>, which is the default, means that no 
flattening takes place, so the array appearing on port <port>source</port> will
be contained as an array in the resulting array. An integer value of <literal>1</literal>
means that an array on port <port>source</port> is flattened, i.e. the members
of that array will appear as individual members in the resulting array. Any value greater
than <literal>1</literal> means that the flattening is applied recursively to arrays in
arrays up to the given depth. A value of “<literal>unbounded</literal>” means that all
arrays in arrays will be flattened. As a consequence, the resulting array appearing on
port <port>result</port> will not have any arrays as members. </para>


<simplesect>
  <title>Document properties</title>
  <para feature="json-join-preserves-none">No document properties are preserved.
The joined document has no <property>base-uri</property>.
</para>
</simplesect>
</section>
