<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:e="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Spec/ElementSyntax"
         xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:id="c.json-merge"
         version="5.0-extension w3c-xproc">
<title>p:json-merge</title>

<para>The <tag>p:json-merge</tag> step merges the sequence of appearing
on port <port>source</port> into a single JSON object appearing on port
<port>result</port>. If the sequence on
port <port>source</port> is empty, the empty sequence is returned on
port <port>result</port>.</para>

<p:declare-step type="p:json-merge">
  <p:input port="source" sequence="true" content-types="any"> </p:input>
  <p:output port="result" content-types="application/json"/>
  <p:option name="duplicates" values="('reject', 'use-first', 'use-last', 'use-any', 'combine')" select="'use-first'"/>
  <p:option name="key" as="xs:string" select="'concat(&#34;_&#34;,$p:index)'" e:type="XPathExpression"/>
</p:declare-step>

<para>The step inspects the documents on port <port>source</port> in turn to create the resulting
  map:</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>If the document under inspection is a JSON document representing a map,
    all key-value pairs are copied into the result map unless this map already contains
    an entry with the given key. In this case the value of option <option>duplicates</option>
    determines the policy for handling duplicate keys as specified for function <code>map:merge</code>
      in <biblioref linkend="xpath31-functions"/>.  
      <error code="C0106">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if duplicate keys are encountered and 
      option <option>duplicates</option> has value “<literal>reject</literal>”.</error></para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>For every other type of JSON document, for XML documents, HTML documents, or text documents a
    new key-value pair is created and put into the resulting map. The key is created by evaluating
    the XPath expression in option <option>key</option> with the inspected document as context item. If the
      evaluation result is a single atomic value, it is taken as key. If the evaluation result is a node, its
      string value is taken as key. <error code="C0110">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the
      evaluation of the XPath expression in option <option>key</option> for a given item returns either a
      sequence, an array, a map, or a function.</error> Duplicate
    keys are handled as described above. The XDM representation of the inspected document is taken as value of
    the key-value pair.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para><impl>It is <glossterm>implementation defined</glossterm> if <code>p:json-merge</code> is
    able to process document types not mentioned yet, i.e. types of binary documents.</impl> If a processor
    supports a given type of documents, the key-value pair is created as described above. <error code="C0107">
    It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if a document of a not supported document type appears on 
      port <port>source</port> of <code>p:json-merge</code>.</error>
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist> 
  <para>An implementation must bind the variable “<code>p:index</code>” in the static context of 
    each evaluation of the XPath expression to the position of the document in the sequence 
    of documents on port <port>source</port>, starting with “<literal>1</literal>”.
    </para>
  <simplesect>
    <title>Document properties</title>
    <para feature="json-merge-preserves-none">No document properties are preserved.
The merged document has no <property>base-uri</property>.
</para>
  </simplesect>
</section>
