<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="c.message">
<title>p:message</title>

<para>The <code>p:message</code> step conditionally produces a message.</para>

<p:declare-step type="p:message">
  <p:input port="source" sequence="true"/>
  <p:output port="result" sequence="true"/>
  <p:option name="test" as="xs:boolean" select="true()"/>
  <p:option name="select" as="item()*" required="true"/>
</p:declare-step>

<para>Steps that produce messages offer one way for an author to keep track of
the progress of a pipeline. The <tag class="attribute">[p:]message</tag>
attribute can be added to any step to display a message when it runs.</para>

<para>Status and debugging messages that are appropriate during pipeline
development may be distracting when the pipeline is running “in production”.
Existing mechanisms for conditional compilation can be used to mediate between
“development” and “production” runs, but they are a bit heavyweight. Adding many
steps with <tag class="attribute">[p:]use-when</tag> attributes and managing the
connections between steps that may be conditionally removed can make pipelines
harder to read and understand.</para>

<para>The <tag>p:message</tag> step can be used to achieve much the same effect
and is considerably less verbose.</para>

<para>If the <tag class="attribute">test</tag> attribute is
  “<literal>true</literal>”, the result of evaluating the <tag class="attribute">select</tag> option is
serialized and made available. (As with the <link
xlink:href="https://spec.xproc.org/master/head/xproc/#messages">message
attribute</link>, this is intentionally vague. <impl>Precisely what “made
available” means is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl>
Often it means “printed on the console”.)</para>

<para>Irrespective of the value of the <tag class="attribute">test</tag>
attribute, the <tag>p:message</tag> passes all of the documents that appear on
its <port>source</port> port through to the <port>result</port> port,
unchanged and in the same order.</para>

<para>If exactly one document appears on the <port>source</port> port, it is the
context item when the <tag class="attribute">test</tag> and <tag
class="attribute">select</tag> expressions are evaluated. In all other cases,
the context item is undefined.</para>

<note>
<para>If it can be determined statically that <tag class="attribute">test</tag> expression is
<emphasis>always</emphasis> “<literal>false</literal>”, the processor may remove the 
step from the pipeline entirely, although it must guarantee that all of the connections
are preserved.</para>
</note>

<simplesect>
  <title>Document properties</title>
  <para feature="message-preserves-all">All document properties are preserved.</para>
</simplesect>
</section>
