<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:e="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Spec/ElementSyntax"
         xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="c.set-properties">
<title>p:set-properties</title>

<para>The <tag>p:set-properties</tag> step sets document
properties on the source document.</para>

<p:declare-step type="p:set-properties">
   <p:input port="source" content-types="any"/>
   <p:output port="result" content-types="any"/>
   <p:option name="properties" required="true" as="map(xs:QName,item()*)"/>
   <p:option name="merge" select="true()" as="xs:boolean"/>
</p:declare-step>

 <para>The document properties of the document
on the <port>source</port> port are augmented with the values specified
in the <option>properties</option> option. The document produced on
the <port>result</port> port has the same representation but the
adjusted property values.</para>

<para feature="p-set-properties-merge">If the <option>merge</option>
option is true, then the supplied properties are added to the existing
properties, overwriting already existing values for a given key. 
If it is false, the document’s properties are replaced by
the new set.</para>

<para><error code="D0070">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if a value is 
assigned to the <code>serialization</code> document property that cannot be converted 
into <code>map(xs:QName, item()*)</code> according
to the rules in section “QName handling” of <biblioref linkend="xproc30"/>.</error></para>

<para><error code="C0069">It is a <glossterm>dynamic
error</glossterm> if the <option>properties</option> map contains
a key equal to the string “<literal>content-type</literal>”.</error>
</para>

<para>If the <option>properties</option> map contains a key equal to the string
“<literal>base-uri</literal>” the associated value is taken as the new base URI of
   the resulting document. <error code="D0064">It is a <glossterm>dynamic 
   error</glossterm> if the base URI is not both absolute and valid according 
      to <biblioref linkend="rfc3986"/>.</error></para>

<simplesect>
<title>Document properties</title>
<para feature="set-properties-preserves-some">If <option>merge</option> is true, document 
properties not overridden by settings in the <option>properties</option> map are preserved, 
otherwise the resulting document has only the <literal>content-type</literal> property and the
properties specified in the <option>properties</option> map. In particular, if <option>merge</option> 
is false, the <literal>base-uri</literal> property will not be preserved. This means that the resulting
document will not have a base URI if the <option>properties</option> map does not contain 
a <literal>base-uri</literal> entry.
</para>
</simplesect>
</section>
