<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:id="c.text-join" xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>p:text-join</title>
  
  <para>The <code>p:text-join</code> step concatenates text documents.</para>
  
  <p:declare-step type="p:text-join">
    <p:input port="source" sequence="true" content-types="text"/>
    <p:output port="result" content-types="text"/>
    <p:option name="separator" as="xs:string?"/>
    <p:option name="prefix" as="xs:string?"/>
    <p:option name="suffix" as="xs:string?"/>
    <p:option name="override-content-type" as="xs:string?"/>
  </p:declare-step>
  
  <para>The <code>p:text-join</code> step concatenates the text documents appearing on its <port>source</port> port
    into a single document on its <port>result</port> port. The documents will be concatenated in order of appearance. </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>When the <option>separator</option> option is specified, its value will be inserted in between adjacent
        documents.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>When the <option>prefix</option> option is specified, the document appearing on the <port>result</port>
        port will always start with its value (also when there are no documents on the <port>source</port>
        port).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>When the <option>suffix</option> option is specified, the document appearing on the <port>result</port>
        port will always end with its value (also when there are no documents on the <port>source</port> port).</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>When the <option>override-content-type</option> option is specified, the document appearing on the port <port>result</port>
    will have this media type as part of its document properties. <error code="D0079">It is a <glossterm>dynamic 
      error</glossterm> if a supplied content-type is not  a valid media type of the form 
      “<literal><replaceable>type</replaceable>/<replaceable>subtype</replaceable>+<replaceable>ext</replaceable></literal>” 
      or “<literal><replaceable>type</replaceable>/<replaceable>subtype</replaceable></literal>”.</error> <error code="C0001">It is a
        <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the value of option <option>override-content-type</option> 
      is not a text media type.</error>
  </para>

  <para>Concatenating text documents does not require identifying individual
lines in each document, consequently no special end-of-line handling is
performed.</para>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Document properties</title>
    <para feature="text-join-preserves-none">No document properties are preserved.
The joined document has no <property>base-uri</property> property.
</para>
  </simplesect>
</section>
