<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:e="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Spec/ElementSyntax"
         xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="c.unwrap">
<title>p:unwrap</title>

<para>The <tag>p:unwrap</tag> step replaces matched elements with their
children.</para>

<p:declare-step type="p:unwrap">
   <p:input port="source" content-types="xml html"/>
  <p:output port="result" content-types="text xml html"/>
   <p:option name="match" as="xs:string" select="'/*'" e:type="XSLTSelectionPattern"/>
</p:declare-step>

 <para>The value of the <option>match</option> option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be an
 XSLTSelectionPattern. <error code="C0023">It is a <glossterm>dynamic
 error</glossterm> if that pattern matches anything other than the document node
 or element nodes.</error></para>

<para>Every element in the <port>source</port> document that matches
the specified <option>match</option> pattern is replaced by its children,
effectively “unwrapping” the children from their parent. Non-element nodes
and unmatched elements are passed through unchanged.</para>

<note xml:id="note-match-doc">
<para>The matching applies to the entire document, not just the “top-most”
matches. A pattern of the form <literal>h:div</literal> will replace
<emphasis>all</emphasis> <tag>h:div</tag> elements, not just the top-most
ones.</para>
</note>

  <para>This step produces a single document. Special cases:</para> 
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>If the document element is unwrapped, the result might not be well-formed XML.</para>
      <para>For instance unwrapping the root element of
          <code><![CDATA[<!-- COMMENT --><root-element/>]]></code> will result in a document node
        with a single comment node child, which is not well-formed.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>If a document consisting of only an empty root element is unwrapped, the result will be
        a document node without children. The result document&#x2019;s content type will not change.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>If a document consisting of a root element containing only text is unwrapped, the result will be
        a document node with a single text node child. The result document&#x2019;s content type will become
        “<literal>text/plain</literal>”.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  
  <para>As specified in the core language specification: if the content type changes, the
      <code>serialization</code> document property, if present, will be removed.</para>
  
<simplesect>
<title>Document properties</title>
  <para feature="unwrap-preserves-partially">If the resulting document contains exactly one text node,
    the <literal>content-type</literal> property is changed to <literal>text/plain</literal> and the 
    <literal>serialization</literal> property is removed, while all other document properties are 
    preserved. In all other cases, all document properties are preserved.</para>
</simplesect>
</section>
