<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:e="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Spec/ElementSyntax"
         xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="c.uuid">
<title>p:uuid</title>

<para>The <tag>p:uuid</tag> step generates a
<biblioref linkend="bib.uuid"/> and injects it into
the <port>source</port> document.</para>

<p:declare-step type="p:uuid">
  <p:input port="source" primary="true" content-types="xml html"/>
  <p:output port="result" content-types="text xml html"/>
  <p:option name="match" as="xs:string" select="'/*'" e:type="XSLTSelectionPattern"/>
  <p:option name="version" as="xs:integer?"/>
</p:declare-step>

<para>The value of the <option>match</option> option must be an
XSLTSelectionPattern. The value of the <option>version</option> option
must be an integer.</para>

<para>If the <option>version</option> is specified, that version of
UUID must be computed. <error code="C0060">It is a <glossterm>dynamic
error</glossterm> if the processor does not support the specified
<option>version</option> of the UUID algorithm.</error> <impl>If the
<option>version</option> is not specified, the version of UUID
computed is
<glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl></para>

<para>Implementations <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> support version 4 UUIDs.
<impl>Support for other versions of UUID, and the mechanism by which
the necessary inputs are made available for computing other versions,
is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl>
</para>

<para>The matched nodes are specified with the <glossterm>selection pattern</glossterm> in the
<option>match</option> option. For each matching node, the generated
UUID is used in the output (if more than one node matches, the
<emphasis>same</emphasis> UUID is used in each match). Nodes that do not
match are copied without change.</para>

<para>If the expression given in the <option>match</option> option
matches an <emphasis>attribute</emphasis>, the UUID is used as the new
value of the attribute in the output. If the attribute is named “<tag class="attribute">xml:base</tag>”, the base URI of the element
<rfc2119>must</rfc2119> also be amended accordingly.</para>

<para>If the document node is matched, the entire document is replaced by a text node
with the UUID. What appears on port <port>result</port> is a text document with the
text node wrapped in a document node.</para>

<para>If the expression matches any
other kind of node, the entire node (and <emphasis>not</emphasis> just
its contents) is replaced by the UUID.</para>

<simplesect>
<title>Document properties</title>
  <para feature="uuid-preserves-partially">If the resulting document contains exactly one text node,
    the <literal>content-type</literal> property is changed to <literal>text/plain</literal> and the 
    <literal>serialization</literal> property is removed, while all other document properties are 
    preserved. For other document types, all document properties are preserved.</para>
</simplesect>
</section>
