<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xml:id="c.xslt">
  <title>p:xslt</title>
  <para>The <tag>p:xslt</tag> step invokes an XSLT stylesheet.</para>
  <p:declare-step type="p:xslt">
    <p:input port="source" content-types="any" sequence="true" primary="true"/>
    <p:input port="stylesheet" content-types="xml"/>
    <p:output port="result" primary="true" sequence="true" content-types="any"/>
    <p:output port="secondary" sequence="true" content-types="any"/>
    <p:option name="parameters" as="map(xs:QName,item()*)?"/>
    <p:option name="static-parameters" as="map(xs:QName,item()*)?"/>
    <p:option name="global-context-item" as="item()?"/>
    <p:option name="populate-default-collection" as="xs:boolean?" select="true()" />
    <p:option name="initial-mode" as="xs:QName?"/>
    <p:option name="template-name" as="xs:QName?"/>
    <p:option name="output-base-uri" as="xs:anyURI?"/>
    <p:option name="version" as="xs:string?"/>
  </p:declare-step>
  <para>If <option>output-base-uri</option> is relative, it is made absolute against the base URI of
    the element on which it is specified (<tag>p:with-option</tag> or <tag>p:xslt</tag> in the case
    of a syntactic shortcut value).</para>
  <para>If the step specifies a <option>version</option>, then that version of XSLT
    <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be used to process the transformation. <error code="C0038">It is a
      <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the specified xslt version is not available.</error> If
    the step does not specify a version, the implementation may use any version it has available and
    may use any means to determine what version to use, including, but not limited to, examining the
    version of the stylesheet. <impl>It is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm> which XSLT
    version(s) is/are supported.</impl></para>
  <para>The XSLT stylesheet provided on the <port>stylesheet</port> port is invoked. <error
    code="C0093"> It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if a static error occurs during the
    static analysis of the XSLT stylesheet.</error> Any parameters passed in the
    <option>parameters</option> option are used to define top-level stylesheet parameters.</para>
  <para>Parameters passed in the <option>static-parameters</option> option are passed as static
    parameters to the XSLT invocation. <impl>Whether static parameters are supported is
      <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm> and depends on the XSLT version (which must be
    3.0 or higher).</impl> If static parameters are not supported the option is ignored.</para>
  <para><error code="C0095">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if an error occurred during
    the transformation.</error>
    <error code="C0096">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the transformation is
      terminated by XSLT message termination.</error>
    <impl>How XSLT message termination errors are reported to the XProc processor is
      <glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>.</impl> Implementations
    <rfc2119>should</rfc2119> raise an error using the error code from the XSLT step (for example,
    the <tag class="attribute">error-code</tag> specified on the <tag>xsl:message</tag> or
    <code>Q{http://www.w3.org/2005/xqt-errors}XTTM9000</code> if no code is provided).</para>
  <para>If XSLT 2.0 or XSLT 3.0 is used, the outputs of this step <rfc2119>may</rfc2119> include
    PSVI annotations.</para>
  <para>The interpretation of the input and output ports as well as for the other options depends on
    the selected XSLT version.</para>
  
  <section>
    <title>Invoking an XSLT 3.0 stylesheet</title>
    <para>The value of <option>global-context-item</option> is used as global context item for the
      stylesheet invocation. If no value is supplied, the following applies:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If there is a single document on the <port>source</port> port, this document will
          become the value of the <option>global-context-item</option> option.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If there are none or multiple documents on the <port>source</port> port, the
          global context item is absent.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The <option>populate-default-collection</option> option is used to control whether all
    the documents appearing on <port>source</port> port form the default collection for the XSLT
    transformation.</para>
    <para>If no value is supplied for <option>template-name</option> option an “Apply-template
      invocation” is performed. The documents that appear on <port>source</port> are taken to be the
      initial match selection. if <option>populate-default-collection</option> is true, they
      are also the default collection. If a value is supplied for 
      the <option>initial-mode</option> option,
      this value is used as the initial-mode for the invocation. <error code="C0008">It is a
        <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the stylesheet does not support a given mode.</error> 
      If no value is supplied, nothing is supplied to the invocation,
      so the default behaviour defined for XSLT 3.0 could be applied.</para>
    <para>If a value is supplied for option <option>template-name</option> a “Call template
      invocation” is performed. The documents on port <port>source</port> are taken as the default
      collection in this case. Option <option>initial-mode</option> is ignored. <error code="C0056"
        >It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the stylesheet does not provide a given
        template.</error></para>
    <para>Independent of the way the stylesheet is invoked, the principal result(s) will appear on
      output port <port>result</port> while secondary result(s) will appear on output port
      <port>secondary</port>. <impl>The order in which 
        result documents appear on the <port>secondary</port> port is
        <glossterm>implementation dependent</glossterm>.</impl> 
      Whether the raw results are delivered or a result tree is
      constructed, depends on the (explicit or implicit) setting for attribute
      <literal>build-tree</literal> of in the output-definition for the respective result. If a
      result tree is constructed, the result will be a text document if it is a single text node
      wrapped into a document node. Otherwise it will be either an XML document or an HTML document
      depending on the attribute <literal>method</literal> on the output-definition for the
      respective result. If no result tree is constructed, the stylesheet invocation may
      additionally deliver a sequence of atomic values, maps, or arrays. For each item in this
      sequence a JSON document will be constructed and appear on the steps output port.</para>
    <para>Option <option>output-base-uri</option> sets the base output URI per XSLT 3.0
      specification. If a final result tree is constructed, this URI is used to resolve a relative
      URI reference. If no value is supplied for <option>output-base-uri</option>, the base URI of
      the first document in the <port>source</port> port's sequence is used. If no document is
      supplied on port <port>source</port> the base URI of the document on port <port>stylesheet</port>
      is used. <error code="C0121">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if a document appearing
        on the <port>secondary</port> port has a base URI that is not both absolute and 
        valid according to <biblioref linkend="rfc3986"/>.</error></para>
    <note>
      <para>If no result tree is constructed for one of secondary results, a sequence of documents
        sharing the same value for attribute <literal>href</literal> may appear on output port
        <port>result</port>.</para>
    </note>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Invoking an XSLT 2.0 stylesheet</title>
    <para>If a sequence of documents is provided on the <port>source</port> port, the first document
      is used as the initial context node. The whole sequence is also the default collection. If no
      documents are provided on the <port>source</port> port, the initial context node is undefined
      and the default collection is empty. <error code="C0094">It is a <glossterm>dynamic
        error</glossterm> if any document supplied on the source port is not an XML document, an
        HTML documents, or a Text document if XSLT 2.0 is used.</error></para>
    <para>The <option>populate-default-collection</option> option is used to control whether all
      the documents appearing on <port>source</port> port form the default collection for the XSLT
      transformation.</para>
    <para>The value of option <option>global-context-item</option> is ignored if a stylesheet is
      invoked as per XSLT 2.0. The invocation of the transformation is controlled by the
      <option>initial-mode</option> and <option>template-name</option> options that set the
      initial mode and/or named template in the XSLT transformation where processing begins. <error
        code="C0007">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if any key in
        <option>parameters</option> is associated to a value which is not an instance of the XQuery
        1.0 and XPath 2.0 Data Model, e.g. with a map, an array, or a function.</error>
      <error code="C0008">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the specified initial mode
        cannot be applied to the specified stylesheet.</error> 
      <error code="C0056">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the specified template 
        name cannot be applied to the specified stylesheet.</error>
    </para>
    <para>The primary result document of the transformation, if there is one, appears on the
      <port>result</port> port. At most one document can appear on the <port>result</port> port.
      All other result documents appear on the <port>secondary</port> port. <impl>The order in which 
        result documents appear on the <port>secondary</port> port is
        <glossterm>implementation dependent</glossterm>.</impl>
    </para>
    <para>The <option>output-base-uri</option> option sets the context's output base URI per the
      XSLT 2.0 specification, otherwise the base URI of the <port>result</port> document is the base
      URI of the first document in the <code>source</code> port's sequence. If no document is
      supplied on port <port>source</port> the base URI of the document on port <port>stylesheet</port>
      is used. <error code="C0121">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if a document appearing
        on the <port>secondary</port> port has a base URI that is not both absolute and 
        valid according to <biblioref linkend="rfc3986"/>.</error></para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Invoking an XSLT 1.0 stylesheet</title>
    <para>The document provided for <port>source</port> is used the transformations source tree.
      <error code="C0039">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the source port does not
        contain exactly one XML document or one HTML document if XSLT 1.0 is used.</error> The
      values supplied for options <option>global-context-item</option>,
      <option>initial-mode</option>, and <option>template-name</option> are ignored. If XSLT 1.0
      is used, an empty sequence of documents <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> appear on the
      <port>secondary</port> port. An XSLT 1.0 step <rfc2119>should</rfc2119> use the value of the
      <option>output-base-uri</option> as the base URI of its output, if the option is
      specified.</para>
    <para>The key/value pairs supplied in <option>parameters</option> are used to set top-level
      parameters in the stylesheet. If the value is an atomic value or a node, its string value is
      supplied to the stylesheet. <error code="C0105">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if an XSLT 1.0
      stylesheet is invoked and option <option>parameters</option> contains a value that is not an atomic value
      or a node.</error>
    </para>
  </section>
  <simplesect>
    <title>Document properties</title>
    <para feature="xslt-preserves-none">No document properties are
    preserved. The <property>base-uri</property> property of each
    document will reflect the base URI specified by the tranformation.
    If the transformation does not establish a base URI, the document
    will not have one.
</para>
  </simplesect>
</section>
